Let's start now with lecture number 10 and
this is about file systems.
So
You have the written instructions here. As
always from the book we use in the course
and also the extra facultative reading
if you want to have a look.
So this lecture is about file systems and
I guess
at least some of the concepts we will discuss
here, you should be pretty familiar with
them. There are two things that are very
connected to the file system that you see
and use every day and that would be files and
directories, so I think this lecture is sort
of
easier than others because
some of the concepts you should be very familiar
with them, but nonetheless the objectives
of this lecture
are to explain the function of file systems
and also which interfaces we have.
We will discuss of course trade offs. As always
when it comes to how we manage the file system,
maintain the information and so on, we will
discuss protection mechanisms that are defined
in the file system and also different ways
in which you can actually allocate the information
on disk and also keep track of which parts
of the disk are free. If you have to write
something new and which are already taken.
This is the agenda. Let's go one step at the
time. So let's start with the first part here:
file concept.
So what extra information, what overheads,
interfaces does the operating system
needs to
provide
In order to provide files and directories,
such type of abstractions to the users and
let me say something before we start. So now
we have discussed memory,
different allocation schemes and also virtual
memory and all these concepts in the last
two lectures. So you will see that there are
parallelisms between what we discussed in
those lectures and what we're going to discuss
today.
But there are also aspects that are very specific
to the file system.
So,
a file if you want to give a definition for
it, it's the minimum allocation unit for the
user when the user decides to store something
on the disk, the minimum it can store is a
file.
This is the abstraction that is introduced by the
operating system and the idea here is to give
this high-level abstraction that
is the file so that the operating system under
the hood takes care of all the
extra steps and interactions with the hardware,
you know this we mentioned from the very
beginning of the course of this ugly interfaces
that you don't really want to talk to directly,
but you can just interact with through
the operating system.
Again, there is a separation between logical
and physical representation, and this is again
thanks to this abstraction that is the file
and similarly the abstraction that is
the directory.
And you already know that
it's not just an abstraction, the file. Actually
each file comes with meta data that is both
for the sake of the operating system, but
also for the sake of the user. OK, you have
different types of files, some are
text file so you can have binary files. Some
are about programs that can be run and so.
Now, one thing that is important to understand
here is that for the majority of files, what
the file is and what the computer should do
to interact with such a file is actually defined
by who creates the file.
So if you double click a text file and Microsoft
Word opens up and you can text on it, it's
because there is a
quite complicated complex series of steps
in between and these are these exist becauses
some of the metadata associated to the file
says this is a text file and the operating
system associate's text files with specific
programs so that actually when you want to
open a file what you do is not just opening
the file but rather telling the operating
system to start a specific process and then
pass that file to that process because
somehow it has been registered at the operating
system level that this specific file, let's
say a text file,
is usually managed, read written modified
with a specific program that needs to be into
execution in needs to be brought up into execution
before you actually access the file.
Some of these things are done with this metadata
that we have in the files that are the attributes
of the file. Of course you have the name.
I'm saying simple stuff. Here we have identifiers.
Here different types for each file you need
to keep the location, so actually some information
that allows the operating system to go and
read in the specific position in the disk
where the file is
stored you have the size you have different
protection levels in might read the file or
execute the file depending on what attributes
or how the protection attributes are set.
And you have time, date and other identification.
So again, pretty simple what I'm saying
I don't think I'm saying anything
too complex here, but if you think, for example
at the process of compiling a lot of
C files so that you create a binary. You
probably know that when you compile your project,
you don't necessarily recompile all the files,
but you might compile only the ones that have
changed since the last time you compiled.
This is a good thing because it requires less
time for you to compile something,
but now you probably see that if you have
such a feature is because of the attributes
you add in the file, so you have
an attribute time and the process you run
to deal with text files that contain instructions
when you want to make them into a binary can
also use these attributes like the time so
that they can check what is the time at which
the last binary was or the last compiled version
of the file was created. You can check what
was the time it was modified last and depending
on this it can decide whether it's
the case that the source file needs to be
compiled again or not so you can see there
are a lot of things happening thanks to the
metadata the attributes you have for each
file.
Here you have a list. I don't think I need
to go through it. It's pretty simple, but
basically is what I said before, that each
file has an extension and the operating system
knows what to do with each file. Also based
on the extension you have so it can associate
different processes that should be started
before you actually operate on the file.
Now the operating system gives you a lot of
functionality to operate with files. It's
not just the abstraction per-se.
The operating system of course needs to maintain
extra information as always to allow for this
functionality and as we saw when we started
discussing processes some information
is specific to individual files or individual
processes, while other information is global.
It applies to the entire system. The operating
system keeps an open file table which tracks
which files are open. Pointers for each file,
so that if you are doing a sequential read,
for example, it can keep track of the last
thing that was read or written to specific
file.
It needs to keep a counter for each file.
Imagine different processes are reading from
the same file. Then the operating system might
read the file only once from disk and then
give this to several processes. But if one
of the processes closes the file, it doesn't
mean that the file should be removed from the
memory. There could be other processes that
are still reading the file and this is why
the operating system must also account for
each file. It keeps the location on the disk.
This is clear the access right and
several other things we will see now during
the lecture. So again, in summary, we need
extra information. Some is specific
to the file or to the process that you are
using to interact with the file. You in this
case is the user or the programmer.
And then some information is global and
it applies to the entire system.
It gives you, of course, also functionality
to operate on files. You can create /
write files at specific locations. You
can read files you can reposition within files.
You can go at different offsets inside the
file, you can delete files, truncate files and
so on. And everything looks pretty simple.
I don't think I'm saying anything too fancy
that is too fancy here, but again
at this point, you should probably have this
feeling that actually opening a file requires
a decent amount of steps you need to interact
with the disk that will be system calls. You
need to locate where the file is on disk.
You need to read something and associate with
the process. That process might be in waiting
state. So you need a mechanism to decide where
to put what you're reading. You might
be swapping out processes, and if you swap
out processes that are waiting for stuff from
the disk, then you should keep these things
that are being
read from the disk in
a specific location so that it doesn't affect
they are not affected by the fact that you
are swapping out processes and so on.
Here we can just look at a very simple
example.
This is a program that copies a file. You
give the input file and you specify where
it should be, or the destination where you
want to copy the file. I ask you to go through
this code and
basically check it. It's not complicated,
but what I'm trying to say here is that you
see
When I say open
read-only
and you specify here, for example, the location
where the file is,
this is actually resulting in a long and complicated
series of steps, and all these things are
done by the operating system and they simplify
your life because it's not you who has to
interact directly with the disk to
specify in which blocks (we will see what these
are) the file is stored whether it is contiguous
blocks, whether it's scattered around the disk,
and so on and so forth. I am not going now through the
pseudocode, have a look at this point
it should be
pretty clear. Here you have this read,
write, close the file and so on.